THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
字幕：破烂熊
校对、调轴、格式化：Obster-Y@github
仅供交流  严禁商用
翻译: 懂得不懂 时间轴: xo & 小朱儿
校对: tpring
大白天下
这份报告我仍然不满意 Humphrey
I am still not happy with this report, Humphrey.
好的大臣 我们很乐意为您重新起草
Then Minister, we shall be happy to redraft it for you.
-你们已经重新起草三次了  -这么说不准确
- You have redrafted it three times already. - That's not absolutely correct.
准确 Bernard 我会数数 这是第三稿
Yes, it is, I can count. This is the third draft report.
对 就是说先起草了一次
Yes, quite so, Miniser, Therefore it has been drafted once
然后重新起草了两次
and subsequently redrafted twice.
别钻牛角尖 Bernard
Don't quibble, Bernard.
我们很乐意起草第三次
We shall be happy to redraft a third time.
还有第四次 第五次 肯定还有第六次
And a fourth and fifth. And a sixth, no doubt.
里面说的还不是我想说的 是你想说的
And it still not say what I want it to say, It say what you want it to say.
-我只想说我想说的  -您想说什么?
- And I want it to say what I want it to say. - What do you want it to say, Minister?
我们想要它说你想说的
We want it to say what you want it to say.
本部门当然不想要您说您不想说的
I'm sure the department dosen't want it to say anything you don't want it to say.
不要再绕了
Stop wittering!
六周前 智库找我们要
Six weeks ago, The Think Tank asked us
公务员过剩的证词
for our evidence on Civil Service overmanning.
我向公务员一字一句布置了三回
Three times I have briefed a group of civil servants in words of one syllable
每次他们交来的报告都不知所云
and each time they've sent back an totally unintelligible report,
和我要他们说的刚好相反
saying the exact opposite of what I asked them to say.
恕我直言 大臣 如果它不知所云
With respect, Minister, how do you know it says the opposite
您怎么知道刚好相反?
if it's totally unintelligible?
我只想说公务员系统
All I am saying is that the Civil Service
严重超编 必须裁员
is grossly overmanned and that must be slimmed down.
正是 报告也是这个意思
Quite so. That is what the report says.
-才不是呢  -是 就是
- No, it doesn't. - Yes, it does.
才不... 听好 我说的是分阶段
No, it... Look, what I'm talking about is a phased reduction
裁掉20万名公务员
in the Civil Service of about 200,000 people.
你到底能不能写进报告里?
Are you going to put that in this report or not?
大臣 您本周末拿回去好好研究一番
Well Minitser, perhaps If you [?] take that draft home in this weekend and study it,
也许会发现它说的正是此意
you might find that it dose in fact saying what you want it to say.
-要是没有呢  -我们总可以重新起草
- And if it doesn't? - Then I can only suggest that we redraft it.
Humphrey 坐下
Humphrey, sit down.
我明白地问 你能明白回答我吗?
Will you give me a straight answer to a straight question?
好吧 大臣 只要您不要求我诉诸
Oh, well, Minister, as long as you are not asking me to resort
简单粗拙或者大而化之的概括
to crude generalizations and vulgar over simplifications,
比如“是”或“不是” 我将尽全力服从
such as a simple yes or no I shall do my utmost to oblige.
意思是“是”?
Is that "yes"?
-是  -好
- Yes. - Right.
-问题来了  -我以为刚才那个就是
- Well, here is the straight question. - Oh I thought that was it.
你给研究所的证词 会不会支持我的观点
When you give your evidence to the Think Tank, are you going to support my view
说公务员严重超编?
that the Civil Service is overmanned [?] or not?
是或不是
Yes or no!
讲明白!
Straight answer!
大臣 您一定要我明白地讲
Well Minister, If you ask me for a straight answer
我只能说 就目前情况
then I shall say that, as far as we can see,
综观全局 纵览古今
looking at it by and large, taking one time with another,
考虑各部门平均水平
in terms of the average of departments,
分析总结 也许可以认为
then in the final analysis it is probably true to say
综上所述 概括说来
that at the end of the day, in general terms,
您很可能发现
you would probably find that
尽管也许不中听
not to put too fine a point on it,
无论如何 恐怕前景微妙
there probably wasn't very much in it one way or the other.
现阶段只能如此预期
As far as one can see...at this stage.
你说“是”还是“不是”?
Is that "yes"? Or "no"?
是也不是
Yes and no.
如果不要你明白回答呢?
Suppose you weren't asked for a straight answer?
我会尽量争取时间 大臣
Then I should play for time, Minister.
Humphrey爵士
Sir Humphrey.
-啊 Bernard 请坐  -谢谢
- Ah, Bernard, sit down. - Thank you.
-你能来太好了  -我很荣幸
- Good of you to pop in. - It's my pleasure.
Bernard 你知道部里那份给
Bernard, you know the Department's report
中央政策评估小组的报告吗?
on the Central Policy Review staff?
知道 Humphrey爵士
Er, yes, Sir Humphrey.
我们还没从大臣那里拿回来
We haven't had it back from the Minister yet.
-是的 没有拿来  -为什么没有?
- No, Sir Humphrey. - Why not?
这个 也许您应该问大臣本人
Er... perhaps you should ask the Minister.
-不 我就问你 Bernard  -是 Humphrey爵士
- No, I'm asking you, Bernard. - Yes, Sir Humphrey.
你好像吞吞吐吐的 Bernard
You don't seem to be replying, Bernard.
是也不是 Humphrey爵士
Yes and no, Sir Humphrey.
-Bernard 你在搪塞我吗?  -绝对没有
- Bernard, are you trying to be impertinent? - Oh no.
要是我真想搪塞 会成功的
I'm sure I would succeed if I tried.
-请来杯加冰威士忌  -好的 先生 就一杯吗?
- [?] me a Scotch on the rocks, please. - Yes, sir. One, sir?
对 就一杯
Yes, just one.
Bernard 大臣在好好批公文吗?
Bernard, Has the Minister been doing his boxes properly?
-当然 他非常尽责  -那到底怎么了?
- Oh, Yes, of course, he's very conscientious. - Then what's going on?
-请您去问大臣  -我问你
- Er, perhaps you should ask the Minister. - No, I'm asking you.
但我是大臣的秘书 要对他负责
But I am the Minister's Principal PRIVATE Secretary, I'm responsible to him.
没错 但你也是公务员
Indeed you are, but you are also a public servant.
大臣的平均任期不到11个月
The average Minister's tenure is less than eleven months, Bernard
你可要干到65岁 对吗?
but your career in the civil service will last until you're 65, won't it?
-对 我希望能  -我也希望 Bernard
- I hope so. - Yes, So do I, Bernard.
不过 你自己拿主意
However, the choice is yours.
呃 Humphrey爵士
Er, Sir Humphrey...
能否请教一个假设的问题?
Can I ask you a hypothetical question?
这总是个好办法
That's always a good idea.
好 如果有位大臣 一位完全假设的大臣
Well, suppose a Minister, a purely hypothetical Minister,
不满意本部门
were to be unhappy with a departmental draft
对某委员会的证词草案
of evidence to a committee.
如果这名大臣企图
And suppose that Minister were planning to replace it
自己重写 参考政治顾问
with his own draft worked out with his political adviser
-和他的政党...  -我不敢相信
- and people from his party... - I can't believe it.
不不 这纯粹是假设
Oh, no, no, of course, but It's purely hypothetical.
如果这位大臣打算
And suppose that Minister were planning to bring in
拖延交稿 让本部门没有时间...
his own draft so close to the final date for evidence that there won't be any time...
-不会  -不会
- Wouldn't... - Wouldn't
有时间重新起草
be any time for the Department to redraft it for him.
怎样?
Well?
如果这位假设大臣的首席私人秘书
Suppose this hypothetical Minister's Principal Private Secretary
知道了这份
were to be aware of this
假设的文件 当然出于信任
hypothetical draft, in confidence of course,
他该不该透露给这个假设部门的
should he pass on this information to the Permanent Secretary
常任秘书?
of this hypothetical department?
当然不该 Bernard
Certainly not, Bernard.
既然这名首席私人秘书出于信任
Not if this Principal Private Secretary had been given
才得到的消息
the information in confidence.
我也这么认为 Humphrey爵士
That's what I thought, Sir Humphrey.
来一杯 Bernard?
Have a drink, Bernard.
还有件事 大臣
There just one more thing, Minister.
给中央政策评估小组的报告
The evidence to the Central Policy Review Staff.
-你说智库?  -对 大臣
- You mean the Think Tank? - Yes, Minister.
-怎样?  -你是不是重新起草了你草案的草案?
- What about it? - Have you redrafted the redraft of your draft?
-你不是要拿回去吧?  -正是
- You don't want it yet, do you? - Yes.
-为什么?  -好为您重新起草
- Why? - So that we can redraft it.
-没有必要  -我认为有 大臣
- Well that won't be necessary. - I think it will, Minitser.
Humphrey 起草文件不是公务员的特权 知道吗?
Humphrey, Drafting is not a Civil Service monopoly, you know?
不 这是门艰深的技艺
No, it's a highly specialised skill
非公务员很难掌握
which few outside the Service can master.
胡说 起草最容易了
Nonsense. Drafts is easy.
人人都能玩一把
It's a game anyone can play.
想玩转就难了
Not without getting huffed.
能否请您把草案还给我?
So could I have the draft proposal, please?
没问题 Humphrey
Certainly, Humphrey.
-什么时候 大臣?  -过一阵 Humphrey
- When, Minister? - Later, Humphrey.
对 但是具体什么时候?
Yes, but when?
你总说做事不能操之过急
You always say we musn't rush things.
大臣 我必须请您明白答复
Minister, I must ask you for a straight answer.
哪天?明天?周一?周二?
On what day? Tomorrow? Monday? Tuesday?
适当的时候 Humphrey
In due course, Humphrey.
等机会来临
At the appropriate juncture.
万事俱备
In the fullness of time.
条件成熟
When the moment is ripe.
所有必要程序都走完
When the necessary procedures have been completed.
当然不会贸然给你
Nothing precipitate, of course.
大臣 这事很紧急
Minister, this is getting urgent.
紧急 Humphrey?今天新词不少么
Urgent, Humphrey? What a lot ot new words we are learning!
大臣 请恕我冒昧
Minister, You'll forgive me if I say this,
但我开始怀疑
but I am beginning to suspect
您对我隐瞒了什么
that you are concealing something from me.
我们两个之间没有秘密 对吗Humphrey?
Surely? You and I have no secrets from each other, have we Humphrey?
抱歉 大臣 但有时人不得不想到
I'm sorry, but sometimes one is forced to consider
事情可能受到操纵
the possibility that affairs are being conducted in a way
考虑一切情况 前思后想
which all things being considered, and making all possible allowances
尽管可能比较刺耳
is, not to put too fine a point on it,
也许您不完全坦率
perhaps not entirely straightforward.
坦率不坦率你最懂了
You're the expert on straightforwardness.
那给政策评估小组的草案怎么说?
So what about the draft evidence to the Central Policy Review Staff?
好吧 既然你问了 Humphrey 还问的这么坦率
Well since you ask, Humphrey, and to be perfectly straightforward,
我自己重新起草了一遍
I have redrafted it myself.
我不要你再改
I don't want you to redraft it.
我非常喜欢它现在的样子
I'm perfectly happy with it as it is.
我能否斗胆问句您写了什么?
May I be bold enough to ask what you have said?
就是我想说的 分阶段裁减公务员
I said what I wanted to say: Phased reductions in the Civil Service.
-好的 但是  -Humphrey 你挫败了我的透明政府
- Yes, but I... - Humphrey, You have frustrated me over open government,
挫败了我的节约运动 这次我可志在必得
You have frustrated me over the economy drive, but this time I'm going to have my way.
政党需要它 公众也需要
The party wants it, the public wants it.
我不得不说 公务员只会采取拖延战术
And I am bound to say all we get from the Civil Service is delaying tactics.
公务员的拖延不能叫“战术”，大臣
Well I wouldn't call Civil Service delays "tactics", Minister,
这是把消极当积极
that would be to mistake lethargy for strategy.
很好笑 Humphrey
Very droll, Humphrey.
但你必须了解 改革是当务之急
But you must realise there is a real desire for radical reform in the air.
党派联席特别行政委员会
Your Party Select Committee on Administrative Affairs,
由我建立 非常之成功
which I founded, it's a casing point, it's a great success.
哦 是吗 有什么成就?
Oh, indeed, what has it achieved?
眼下没有 不过我们党派很喜欢
Nothing yet. The party's very pleased with it.
为什么?
Why?
首先 上周一《每日邮报》10吋的专栏
Ten column inches in last Monday's Daily Mail for staff.
如今政府以专栏长度论成败啦?
Oh I see, The government is going to measures its success in column inches, is it?
是...不是...
Yes... no...
是也不是
Yes and no!
大臣 您要提交的证词
Minister, the evidence that you are proposing to submit
不仅不真实 更有甚者 还不明智
is not only untrue, it is also, which is much more serious, unwise.
这件事我们讨论过
Now, we have been through all this before.
公务员编制庞大
The expansion of the Civil Service
是议会立法的结果
is the result of parliamentary legislation,
与官僚帝国无关
not bureaucratic empire building.
下次质询 你要我告诉议会
So when the next coming up question time you want me to tell Parliament that it's their fault
是他们害公务员队伍这么庞大?
that the Civil Service is too big?
-可这是事实 大臣  -我不要事实
- But it's the truth, Minister. - I don't want the truth.
我要给议会一个交待
I want something I can tell Parliament.
Humphrey 你是我的常任秘书 应该执行我的政策
Humphrey, you are my Permanent Secretary, you are supposed to enact my policies.
可你怎么专门跟我作对
Yet, I still not understand why you seem implacably opposed to me.
我必须知道你站在那边
I must know where you stand on all this.
大臣 一个人站的立场 取决于他坐的位置
Where one stands, Minister, depends upon where one sits.
我猜你是不支持我了?
Am I to infer that you will not support me?
我们永远支持您 大臣
We will always support you, Minister
但要给您扛旗 而不是抬棺材
but as your standard bearer not as you pall bearer.
Humphrey 你在说什么呀?
Humphrey, What are you saying?
我认为再清楚不过了 大臣
I should have thought is crystal clear, Minister.
不要把报告交给
Do not send this report to a body
打算发表的人!
whose recommendations are to be published!
我就是要拿去发表
That is exactly why I'm sending it.
我不想再听你说了
I don't want to hear anymore about it.
-我能否再说一件事?  -除非用简单英语
- May I say just one more thing? - Only If it's in plain English.
很好 大臣
Very well, Minister.
如果您非要做这件蠢事
If you are going to do this damn silly thing,
拜托别用这种蠢办法
don't do it in this damn silly way.
大臣 内阁会议您要迟到了
Minister, I'm afraid you'll be late for Cabinet if you don't in a hurry.
哦 对了 内阁
Oh, yes. Cabinet.
今天上午讨论什么?
What are we talking about this morning?
内阁讨论您的提案 关闭土地局
Cabinet is considering your proposals to close down the Land Registry.
我的提案?
My proposal...?
您记得吗 缩减地方自治政府
Yes you remember, Minister? Reducing the number of autonomous Government Departments.
-是你的提案  -您签字了
- That was your proposal. - You have initialled it Minister.
-哦 是吗? 写的什么?  -放心 大臣 绝对一致通过
- Oh, have I? What's in it? - Oh, Never mind Minister, It'll all go through on the nod.
-好吧 东西带齐了?  -齐了
- Got all the stuff? - Yes.
快点 可别迟到
Come on then, mustn't be late.
小汉
Humpy...
你们部门给智库的证词写了吗?
Have you written your deparment evidence to the Think Tank yet?
-多少算吧  -怎么讲?
- More or less. - What do you mean More or less?
-大臣在写  -小汉!
- Well, The Minister's written it. - Humpy!
对对 很不明智 可他一定要写
Yes, I know. All very unwise, but he insisted.
他一个多星期就没干别的
He's been working at nothing else for more than a week now.
你不该让大臣卷进这么深
You should never let Ministers get so deeply involved.
今天写草案 再不盯紧 他们要定政策了呢
Once they start writing the draft, The next thing we know they'll be dictating at policy.
是 我明白
Yes, I know.
-这次会议长吗?  -估计不会
- Is this a lengthy Cabinet? - I don't think so.
纯粹浪费生命
Ghastly waste of time.
没错 可没有我们牵着小手
Yes, but if we're not here to hold their little hands,
天晓得他们会干出什么来?
God knows what they might not get up to?
失陪了 巨人 是 大臣
Excuse me, Jumbo. Yes, Minister?
你知道我提议内阁关闭土地局
I'm recommending to Cabinet to close down the Land Registry.
-是啊?  -为什么?
- Yes? - Why?
-为什么?  -为什么?
- Why? - Why?
为什么关闭还是为什么提上内阁?
Why are we closing it or why we bringing it to Cabinet?
-什么?  -什么?
- What? - What?
我为什么要提上内阁?
Why am I recommending it to the Cabinet?
-您当然知道  -不知道我才问
- Surely you know. - No, that's why I'm asking you. I made the the recommendation.
你说会一致通过 我才提的
You said it would go through on the nod,
现在首相问起来了
now the PM's started asking everybody about very [odd/old] questions.
我自己还没读过
And I haven't read my proposal.
因为地方政府部门扩张了9.75%
Beacure there was a 9.75% rise in a number of autonomous Government Departments.
对对 谢谢你
Yes, of course. Thank you.
抱歉 巨人
I'm sorry about that, Jumbo...
你在限制地方自治政府?
Helping to restrict the growth of autonomous departments?
正好跟首相的政策走
That should find favour with the PM policy-wise.
哦?为什么?
Oh? Why?
最近时兴削减公务员
Very fashionable simplifying the Civil Service
特别是研究所出报告之后
especially with this Think Tank recommendation as well.
-报告还没提交吧  -提交了 私下的
- But they haven't report it. - Yes, they have, unofficially...
不会 证词还没收集全呢
Oh they can't, They haven't taken all the evidence yet.
中央政策评估小组高贵的头脑
The Central Policy Review Staff don't sully their elevated minds
掺不进证据这种沙子
with anything as sordid as evidence.
估计他们正建议首相
You may take it that they'll be advising the PM
简化政府行政部门
to reduce and simplify the administration of government.
那我有得忙了 对吧
Well, that'll keep me busy, I suppose. Ah, well.
我估计不会
I shouldn't count on it.
你不指望我－首相的资深政策顾问
Well you surely don't expect me, the PM's Senior Policy Adviser,
把机密透给一个常任秘书吧
to betray confidences his Permanent Secretary.
当然 透机密怎么能找同事
Well, not to your colleagues, certainly.
反正午饭前你也会听到小道消息
On the other hand, No doubt the grapevine would inform you by lunchtime.
听到?听到什么?
Inform? Inform us of what?
Humphrey 你那位大臣千方百计
Humphrey, you know that Your Minister is always seeking
裁减公务员队伍
to reduce overmanning in the Civil Service.
这回他成功了
Well, he's going to get his way.
财政部 内政部和公务员系统
Treasury, the Home Office and the Civil Service Department
都提议
have all proposed
废除你们行政事务部
to abolish your Department of Administrative Affairs
首相对提案微笑了
and the PM is smiling on the plan.
-真荒唐  -干净利落
- That's absurd. - Clean. Dramatic.
众望所归 没什么阻力
Very popular politically. No real inconvenience.
你们所有的职能都将由其他部门接手
Let's face it all your functions could be subsumed by other departments.
Jim·Hacker大公无私 牺牲自己
Jim Hacker will win through with a thoroughly public [?] self sacrificing policy.
首相会给他挂个职 供起来
The PM will probably kick him upstairs.
神风敢死队Hacker阁下
Lord Hacker of Kamikaze.
Daniel 这一点都不好笑
I hardly think that's funny, Daniel or likely.
怎么? 他领导过反首相运动
Why not? He ran the leadership campaign against the PM, didn't he?
这可是首相精彩的一笔 一蹴而就
This could be the PM's master stroke in one fell swoop.
先招安 再封爵 最后架空
Approbation, elevation and castration.
你知道首相的座右铭
You know the PM's motto
“败则怀恨在心 胜则反攻倒算”
"In Defeat, malice. In Victory, revenge".
废除我的部门
Abolish my Department.
想都不要想
Out of the question.
绝对做不到
Simply can't be done.
你当然最清楚 Humphrey
Well I'm sure you know best, Humphrey.
顺便 马贩街有个就业中心
Oh, By the way, there's a job centre in the Horse Ferry Road.
19路公交 下车即到
The No.19 Bus stops right outside.
-我太震惊了  -你还震惊
- I'm appalled. - You're appalled?
我才震惊呢
I'm appalled.
真不敢相信 我...太震惊了
I just can't believe it. I'm... I'm appalled.
-Bernard 你怎么想?  -我震惊了
- What do you make of it, Bernard? - I'm appalled, Minister.
我也是 震惊啊!
So am I. Appalled!
让人震惊
It's appalling.
震惊
Appalling.
我简直没法形容
I just don't know how to describe it.
-震惊?  -震惊! 可这是真的吗?
- Appalling. - Appalling. But I mean is it true?
他不是吓唬你吧?
You sure he wasn't having you on?
一个部门怎能说废就废
They can't mean to abolish this entire department.
听起来很像真的 对吧?
Well It rings true, doesn't it?
我刚看到了各部门联合提案
I've just see the joint departmental proposal.
白厅里最不缺提案
Whitehall's full of proposals.
Daniel·Hughes是首相的亲信
Daniel Hughes is very close to the PM.
会发生什么?我会去哪呢?
What's going to happen? Where will I go?
有个传闻 大臣
Well, there is a rumour, Minister...
传闻? 什么传闻?
Rumour? What rumour?
工业协调总管大臣
Minister with general responsibility for Industrial Harmony.
工业协调?
Industrial harmony?
你知道这是管什么 罢工啊!
You know what that means, don't you. That means strikes!
今后全英国的罢工都是我的错
From now on every strike in Great Britain will be my fault.
那太好了
Oh, marvellous.
您想过我会怎样吗?
Have you considered what might happen to me?
-没 怎样?  -八成会调到农渔部去
- No. What? - I shall probably be sent to Ag and Fish.
余生都用来讨论鳕鱼配额
The rest of my career dedicated to arguing about the cod quota.
至于你 Bernard
And as for you, Bernard,
你的大臣落了地 你现在的好名声
if your Minister bites the dust, your reputation as a high flyer, such it is,
也全打水漂
will be hit for six.
你的余生大概要
You'll probably spend your career
呆在交通管理中心 在Swansea(威尔士南郊)
in the Vehicle Licensing Centre in Swansea.
-都是你的错  -我的错
- It's your fault, you know. - My fault?
是你提议削减地方自治部门
It was your proposal to reduce the number of autonomous government departments.
是你提议分阶段削减公务员
It was your proposed to carry out phased reductions of the Civil Service.
我们还是别吵了 想想现在怎么办?
Don't let's argue about that. Point is what are we going to do now?
我们可以上书
We could put a paper up.
上什么?
Up what?
-太妙了!  -大臣 您倒说一个?
- Brilliant! - Have you any suggestions, Minister?
-我不知道 我...  -震惊了?
- I don't know, I'm... - Appalled?
大臣 这次我们一定要齐心协力
Minister, I really do think that we should work together on this.
-这话我听过  -什么意思?
- I've heard that before. - What do you mean?
你所谓齐心协力 就是你出主意我出力
You idea about working together is you telling me what to do, me doing it.
-不是的 大臣  -你也没办法?
-Not Minister, that isn't true. - You've no suggestions?
我提议让Bernard叫你的政治顾问来
I suggest Bernard could fetch your Political Adviser.
-Frank? 你要我请教Frank?  -是的拜托 大臣
- Frank? You want me to consult Frank? - Yes, please, Minister.
还有 大臣 恕我直言...
And Minister, with respect...
别跟我说这个 Humphrey
Please, Don't use that language to me, Humphrey.
-说什么?  -我知道什么叫“恕我直言”
- What language? - I know what "with respect" means in your jargon.
你在暗示我的建议全都不值一提
It means you are about to imply anything I suggest is beneath contempt.
啊 大臣
Ah, Minister.
这次我是真想齐心协力
I really do mean that we should work together.
-我需要您  -你说真的 Humphrey?
- I need you. - Do you mean that, Humphrey?
-是 大臣  -Humphrey 你太好了
- Yes, Minister. - Humphrey, how very nice of you.
大臣 如果首相要搞阴谋
Minister, if the Prime Minister is behind a scheme,
光凭白厅制止不了
Whitehall on its own cannot block it.
内阁大臣的阴谋很容易制止...改写
Cabinet Ministers' schemes are easily blocked... redrafted,
但首相就另当别论
but the Prime Minister is another matter.
我们得从议会和白厅两面出击
We need to fight this in Westminster and as well as in Whitehall.
Frank·Weisel动员后座议员
And Frank Weisel might be able to mobilise the backbenchers on your behalf.
对 他也许还能发动媒体
Yes. And what about Fleet Street? And he might be able to mobilise the Press.
-Frank 你听到消息了?  -Bernard刚告诉我
- You've heard the news? - Bernard just told me.
有什么建议?
What do you suggest?
我想不出来...我震惊了
I can't think of anything...I'm appalled.
我们不能跟老母鸡似的自乱阵脚
Mustn't all flap around like a lot of wet hens.
得设法拯救这个部门
We've got to do something to save this Department from closure.
听好 你找组织秘书动员后座议员
Now listen, I want you through the whip's office to get to the backbenchers in Central House
趁它出世之前消灭掉
to put a stop to this thing before it starts.
对不起 可是没出世的东西消灭不着
I'm sorry, Minister, I'm quibble again, but you can't actually stop something before it starts.
多谢了 Bernard。 还有Frank...
Thank you very much Bernard. Frank...
没那么容易 Jim 后座议员非常欢迎
It won't be that easy, you know, Jim. It will actually be a very popular move with backbenchers.
发动舆论呢?大臣 您知道:
What about a publicity campaign, Minister? You know:
“行政救国” “公文之乐”
"Administration Saves the Nation", "Red Tape is Fun".
整版广告登在...
Full page ads in...
我瞎想的
It was just an idea.
“公文之乐”?
"Red Tape is Fun"
“公文连起你我他”呢?
What about "Red Tape holds the Nation together"?
没办法挽回了 已经大白天下了
Well, there's no doubt about it, the writing's on the wall.
反正应该让公众感谢行政部
We have to think something to make the public to think kindly towards Administration,
-为了欧通卡  -就是
- because of the Europass. - Quite.
-欧通卡?  -欧洲统一身份证
- Europass? - European Identity Card.
Bernard 你没告诉大臣?
Bernard, Surely you've informed the Minister?
大臣 您没看公文盒?
Minister, Didn't you do your boxes last night?
没有 我在起草草案的草案呢
No, I was redrafting the redraft of the draft.
简单说 大臣 欧共体即将颁布
Well, briefly, Minister, Brussels is about to decree
一种新的欧洲统一身份证
that there should to be a new European Identity Card
供欧洲共同体全体成员使用
to be carried by all citizens of the EEC
外交部已经准备妥协了
The Foreign Office is quite ready to go along with it
补偿我们硬栽培出去的黄油山
as a quid pro quo for a deal over the butter mountain,
红酒湖 牛奶海
the wine lake, and the milk ocean,
羊肉战 鳕鱼堆
the lamb war, and the cod stink.
很显然 首相要您来提出立法
And quite obviously, the Prime Minister wants you to introduce the legislation.
-我?  -对
- Me? - Yes.
众所周知您是亲欧洲派嘛
Well it's well known that you're pro Europe, you see.
这也能大大简化行政程序
And it would simplify our administration normly in the long run.
-实在是好主意  -好主意?
- So it's a good idea. - Good idea?
-好主意?  -好主意?
- Good idea? - Good idea?
-有什么不好吗?  -这是政治自杀!
- Not a good idea? - Political suicide!
让英国人都带身份证?
Trying to make British people carry compulsory Identification Papers?
他们会说这是极权国家的做法
They'll [?] it a Police State again.
我们打了两次世界大战 就为这个?
Is this what we fought two world wars for, Humphrey?
大臣 这就跟驾驶证差不多
Well Minister, It's really little more than a sort of driving licence.
这是给我落井下石
It's the last nail on my coffin.
您可以改叫它“欧洲快车”
You might get away with calling it "Euroclub Express".
Bernard 要么闭嘴要么出去!
Bernard, either shut up or get out!
为什么是我们 不该归外交部吗?
Why do we have to introduce it, Can't the Foreign Office do it?
首相也这样想
Well in fact, that was the Prime Minister's original suggestion,
但外交部长说归内政部
but the Foreign Secretary thought this was a Home Office matter
内政部说其实
and the Home Office [?took a deal that] it was essentially
这是行政事务 首相同意了
in the administrative matter, and the PM agreed.
都在踢皮球
They are all playing pass the parcel.
里面有定时炸弹 能怪他们吗?
Can you blame them when you can hear it ticking?
恐怕按计划 这个身份卡议案
Well I'm afraid The identity card bill is planned to be
是本部门的收山之作
the last action of this Department.
反欧洲分子该高兴了
Wonderful ammunition for the anti-Europeans.
外交部不知道这会分裂大欧洲吗?
Yes, but don't the Foreign Office realise what the damage this will do to the European idea?
当然知道 所以要支持
Well I'm sure they do. That's why they support it.
外交部该亲欧洲吧?
Well, sure the Foreign Office is pro Europe, isn't it?
是也不是... 原谅我的措辞
Yes and no... if you'll forgive the expression.
外交部亲欧洲 实际是为了反欧洲
The Foreign Office is pro Europe because it is really anti Europe.
公务员团结在这一理念下
The Civil Service was united in its desire to make sure
保证共同市场不能形成
that the Common Market didn't work.
-所以我们打进去  -你在说什么?
- That's why we went into it. - What are you talking about?
大臣 英国的外交目标
Minister, Britain has had the same foreign policy objective
500年来没有变过
for at least the last 500 years:
创造一个分裂的欧洲
To create a disunited Europe.
因此 我们联荷兰制西班牙
In that cause, We have fought with the Dutch against the Spanish,
联德国制法国
with the Germans against the French
联法国和意大利制德国 联法国制德国和意大利
and with the French and Italians against the Germans and with the French against the Germans against the Italians.
分而治之 您看
Divide and rule, you see.
一贯效果很好 为什么要改变?
Why should we change now, when it's worked so well?
这都是老皇历了吧?
That's all ancient history surely?
对 也是现行政策
Yes, and current policy.
我们得打进去 从内部攻破
We had to break the whole thing up, so we had to get inside.
我们施加过外力 没有成效
We tried to break it up from the outside, but that wouldn't work.
现在可以从里面把它搅成一锅粥了
Now, that we are inside we can make a complete pig's breakfast of the whole thing.
挑德国反法国
Set the Germans against the French,
挑法国反意大利 挑意大利反荷兰
the French against Italians, the Italians against the Dutch...
外交部高兴坏了 光辉岁月又回来了
The Foreign Office is terribly pleased, it's just like old times.
但我们都忠于大欧洲理念吧
Surely we're all committed to the European ideal.
诚然 大臣
Really, Minister.
不然为什么要增加成员国?
Why are we pressing for an increase in the membership?
一个道理 就像联合国
Well for the same reason. It's just like the United Nations in fact.
群龙无首 人多嘴杂
The more members it has, the more arguments it can stir up,
它就越发鸡毛蒜皮
the more futile and impotent it becomes.
-这也太世故了吧  -是的
- What appalling cynicism. - Yes.
我们一般叫做外交 大臣
We call it diplomacy, Minister.
别的国家会怎么看身份证?
How will the other EEC countries feel about having a carried identity papers?
它们没意见吗?
Won't they resist too?
没有 德国人正合意 法国人不在乎
No, now the Germans will love it, the French will ignore it,
意大利和爱尔兰乱成一团 根本执行不下去
and the Italians and the Irish will be too chaotic to enforce it.
只有英国人受罪
It's only the British will resent it.
-这是成心陷害我  -反正也要废你的部
- I think It's a plot to get rid of me. - They'll be got rid of it anyway when the Department are abolished.
也许首相要斩草除根
Perhaps the PM wants to make absolutely certain.
-别神经过敏  -大家都要对付你 你也会神经过敏的
- Don't be so paranoid. - Oh no, you will be paranoid if everyone is plotting against you.
-我们支持你 大臣  -对 大臣
- We're on your side, Minister. - Yes, Minister.
-Martin会支持我们  -对 Martin在哪?
- Martin will be on ourside. - Yes that's true, where is Martin?
外交部长大概在下院 大臣 你也该去的
I think the Foreign Secretary is in the House, Minister, where you ought to be.
我们去找他
Let's go and see him.
真让人震惊 Jim
This is appalling, Jim.
-你就像参孙  -参孙?
- You've done a Samson act and [?]. - Samson?
对 你一心想减少公务员 就动手了
Yes You wanted to reduced the Civil Service bureaucracy and you've done it.
摧垮整座大厦 埋葬了你自己
You've pulled the whole superstructure down and buried yourself.
-惨胜不如败  -没办法吗?
- A Pyrrhic victory. - No ideas?
-若能帮忙我当然尽力  -不过我还不明白欧通卡...
- I'd help if I could.- But I don't understand about the Europass...
说不过去
It doesn't make sense.
首相看不到它会危害政府吗?
Why can't the PM see the damage it is going to do to the government?
没错 欧通卡是我入内阁以来
Yes I agree, I think this Europass issue is the biggest disaster of the government
政府最大的危机
since I asked to join the Cabinet.
您当然不是这个意思 大臣
I don't think you quite mean that, Minister.
人人都知道欧通卡行不通
Everybody knows this Europass thing won't happened.
但是为了拿破仑奖  首相一定得玩到底
The PM's got to play along with it didn't until after the Napoleon Prize is awarded.
拿破仑奖?
Napoleon Prize?
北约颁的 五年一次
Yes, It's a NATO award given once every five years.
布鲁塞尔开大会 发金奖牌 10万镑奖金
Gold medal, big ceremony in Brussels, 10,000 Pounds.
这次首相呼声最高
The PM is the front runner this time.
颁给对欧洲统一贡献最大的政治家
It's for the statesman who has made the biggest  contribution to European unity.
拿破仑以降 如果不算希特勒的话
Since Napoleon. That is if you don't count Hitler.
所以呢?
So? What...?
委员会六周后决议
The awards committee sits in six weeks times.
首相不能最后阴沟里翻船
Well obviously the PM isn't going to rock the boat until it's in the bag.
“阴沟里不可翻船” (交通管理中心^_^)
You don't put boats in bags.
-你说什么 Bernard?  -没什么 首相
- What's that Bernard? - Oh, nothing, Minister.
一旦奖到手 首相马上推翻欧通卡
Once the prize is awarded, the PM will obviously dump the Europasses.
Martin 多少人知道拿破仑奖得主?
Martin, How many people know about the winner of the Napoleon Prize?
-这是最高机密  -你是说人人都知道
- It's top secret. - Oh you mean everyone.
-不是 最高最高机密  -就是它了!
- No, top secret top secret. - That's it then.
-Humphrey 你没想到吗?  -想到什么?
- Humphrey, don't you see? - See what?
-后座议员 消息泄漏  -威尔士民族党?
- Backbenchers. Leaks. - The Welsh Nationalist party?
不 不 不
No. No. No.
对不起 外交大臣 我过会再来
Oh sorry Foreign Secretary, I'll come back later.
别 别走 正要找你
No. No. Don't go, the very man.
进来 Daniel
Come on in, Daniel.
-我有一事请教  -我尽量帮忙 大臣
- I want to ask your advice. - I'll give any help I can, Minister.
但要是木已成舟的事
Oh if it's a question of shutting stable doors after horses have bolted,
我也为无力挽回
even I am powerless to help [?at my advised].
这事你能出力
I don't think you will be powerless in this case.
完全是道德困局
It's really a sort of moral dilemma.
假设一名后座议员
Look, supposing a backbencher want to put down
向首相提问 英国会不会接受欧通卡
a question for the Prime Minister, asking whether the Europass...
哪个议员? 欧通卡是最高机密
Which backbencher? Europass is top secret.
跟拿破仑奖得主一样机密吗?
You mean like the winner of the Napoleon Prize is top secret?
我想大臣是说假设有议员
I think the Minister meant a hypothetical backbencher.
正是 Bernard 谢谢你
Quite so, Bernard. Thank you.
一名假设的议员
A hypothetical backbencher.
对首相提了个假设的问题
And a hypothetical question to the PM
问英国是不是会接受欧通卡
asking whether or not Britain was going to adopt the Europass.
-非常不可能  -我同意 非常不可能
- Highly improbable. - Oh, I agree. Highly improbable.
但如果首相说“会”
But suppose the PM were to answer yes,
会打击国内吧?
it would be very damaging in the country?
对
Yes.
如果首相说“不会”
And suppose the PM were to answer no
在欧洲又很尴尬?
it would be very damaging in Europe?
对首相个人来说
To the PM personally.
拿破仑奖方向
Napoleon prize-wise.
好 如果这个假设的首相预先知道了
Now, if a hypothetical Minister were to get to hear
这个假设的问题 他该怎么办?
of this hypothetical question in advance, what should he do?
唯一办法是保证
The [?] obvious course would be to ensure
永远没人会问 很明显
that the question was not tabled, that must be obvious.
压制议员提问 责任重大啊
Serious business, try to suppres a MP's question.
不过 没有别的办法
Nevertheless, there is no other course.
想拦住他 也许只能
The only way to stop him might be to get him
消除他的另一个问题
to put down a question asking the Prime Minister
要首相澄清传说中
to squash the rumours about the closure
废除行政事务部的谣言
of the Department for Administrative Affairs.
哦 我肯定...你怎么会想到...
Oh, but I'm sure... whatever made you think...
没问题 我全力支持
No question about anything but the fullest support...
昨天你还说废除行政部已经提上议程
But you said only yesterday, that a plan to abolish the Department had been put up,
首相还朝它微笑
and the PM was smiling on it.
不 是嘲笑 嘲笑 不是微笑
No, smiling at it! Smiling at it, not on it.
这个主意荒谬绝伦
The whole idea was ridiculous.
可笑 不值一驳
Laughable. Out of the question.
开玩笑
A joke.
开玩笑?
A joke?
当然是玩笑 你不会以为...
Must a joke! You didn't imagine...
那由首相办公室发出备忘录
So that a minute from the Prime Minister's office confirming this,
澄清谣言 会在24小时内
and squashing the rumour, will be circulated to all departments
传遍所有部门吧
within 24 hours.
让大家都看到 玩笑嘛
So that we can all share it, jokewise I mean!
你真觉得有这个必要吗?
Do you really think it's necessary?
有
Yes.
好吧 肯定有办法的
Well, I'm sure something can be arranged.
我先失陪
If you'll excuse me.
将死他了吧
Checkmate, I think.
一击中的
Game, set and match.
Daniel·Hughes能做到吗?
Can Daniel Hughes really fix this?
首相自己有想法的吧?
Don't Prime Ministers have minds of their own?
当然
Certainly.
但正像尼克松总统的亲信说的
But as President Nixon's henchmen once said:
“抓住了他们的要害
"When you've got them by the balls,
他们的意志和头脑就为你所制了”
their hearts and minds will follow".
是不是?
Isn't that right?
正是 大臣
Yes, Minister.